hey so guys my name is Jonah welcome
back to my sea loss loss series so today
I wanted to talk about something a
little bit different in fact I want to
start kind of like a mini series within
this C++ series just talking about
random C++ things like tips and tricks
that kind of stuff that will hopefully
help you guys with some of the more
intricate maybe less known features of
C++ or just traps along the way because
Sabo's was is full traps this basically
just started off with me having a long
list of things that are just weird and
things that I thought that I should
probably mention at some point in this
series but didn't really have either the
time or the necessity or July just
didn't know where to fit them in because
that they're just kind of you know
little small things and this by the way
this is just a prop the list is on
Charlie
but the point is there is much to
discuss about C++ and so this is where
this series comes in so I hope you guys
enjoy it today I wanted to talk about
something called argument evaluation
order so in other words if I write a
function that has a bunch of arguments
and I pass a bunch of arguments into
that function what order do the
arguments get evaluated in because
amongst the arguments I can actually
write expressions which evaluate those
arguments I don't have to pass in the
number five into a function that takes
in an int I can pass X plus y or five
plus eight so if I do that and if I have
a lot of arguments does the first
argument get done first and then the
second argument gets evaluated and the
third one does it go in reverse order
what happens how does this work and the
interesting thing is that most people
don't know most people don't know what
this order of evaluation actually is
what do you think it is pause this video
right now and drop a comment below with
your answer it'll be really interesting
to see what the general community thinks
and don't look it up anyway pretend this
is like a job interview or something
like that and the thing is if you're
wrong or if you don't know the answer I
don't blame you because this is not
something that really comes up in
programming it almost sounds like
something that should actually come up
more often than it does but when you're
actually writing C++ code you don't
really think about this and I think it's
perfectly reasonable to not know the
answer to this because it is
kind of it does involve knowing a little
bit more about how the compiler to
compile occurred what the C++ standard
actually specifies for C++ compilers and
also just a lot of experience I think
will probably lead you to I guess
naturally knowing the answer to this and
we're gonna dive in here and take a look
at some examples and just explore this
general problem but first I want to give
a huge thank you to Skillshare for
sponsoring this video
for those of you who don't know
Skillshare is an amazing online learning
community where millions come together
to take the next step in their creative
journey
it's a massive platform filled with
thousands of inspiring classes for
people who want to learn a new skill
they've got so many amazing classes on
there I particularly like a lot of their
illustration classes for example this
one is pretty cool they've even got
stuff about productivity in general so
how to improve your productivity because
who does not like being productive and
who does not struggle with that and a
$10 per month for an annual subscription
it has great value and a great way to
spend your time learning new skills
Skillshare is offering two months of
free Skillshare premium membership to
the first thousand people who sign up
using the link in the description below
so make sure you guys check that out for
free and learn something new today
speaking of learning something new let's
take a look at this argument evaluation
order shall we okay so here I have a
super simple function called print sum
that just takes in two integers and adds
them together prints the result as well
as the two integers that we're feeding
into it is just a really simple example
which will help illustrate this in
action so let's go ahead and create a
value here let's set it to zero and then
I'm going to call print sum now what I'm
going to do is write an expression here
that needs to get evaluated at some
point so I'm not just going to pass in
value I'm gonna pass in value plus plus
and I will do this twice so this is a
really simple example to illustrate
exactly what I'm talking about
what will be printed and if you still
haven't left a comment please leave one
right now I'm really interested to see
what you guys think and I'll be honest
going through this code I would probably
expect it to be something like maybe 0-4
like this one and then one for this one
if it's evaluating them in reverse order
maybe will in fact be zero and
one obviously this is a post increment
operator meaning that the original value
should get passed in first then
incremented but then again that's just
my guess so I expect a to be either 1 or
0 and then B to be either well 0 or 1
depending on what a was this is probably
what I would guess but then again I
would be wrong because the answer to
this is it's undefined behavior the C++
standard does not actually define what
should happen in the situation which
means it's undefined behavior means that
it's going to vary compiler to compiler
is completely dependent on the actual
implementation of the sample source
compiler that has to then translate this
code into machine code basically that
means this is unreliable and it will be
different so why don't we do some
testing let's go ahead and run this code
right now and see what we get
ok so this is my output 1 plus 0 equals
1 ok interesting so it looks like it
passed in 0 for this first value and
then 1 so I guess I was right when I
said 1 plus 0 equals 1 I'm using the
microsoft visual studio compiler here
MSB C and I'm running in debug mode
let's try release mode and see what we
get
hang on a minute and see your plus 0
equals 0 what so this doesn't work at
all in release mode why does this differ
release mode to debug mode what if I
change this post increment to be a kind
of pre increments on other words it
should increment the value variable
first and then pass it into the function
let's switch both of these to be like
this so in other words now if it follows
that kind of this parameter is evaluated
first in this parameter order we should
get 1 and 2 I guess let's run this code
I'm in release mode now and I get 2 plus
3 equals 4 so the value is just true for
both of these what about running it in
debug mode I also get to boss two equals
4 so this seems kind of I guess at least
deterministic between debug and release
mode but overall the point of this
exercise is so that you can see that
this is a complete mess because it's
undefined behavior you can't predict
this behavior it you're not supposed to
do this now the case that is
particularly interesting to me is this
kind of release mode case of the post
increment operator so in other words 0
plus 0 equals 0 what is even happening
here the reason this is happening is the
the compiler is actually allowed to work
out what these are in parallel it does
not have to first evaluate these
arguments in a specified order to see
what they are know when trying to kind
of figure out what this isn't using like
constant folding in release mode and
various other optimizations that
basically allow you to work out the
value of variables in compiled time so
in other words if I wrote two plus five
instead of actually doing two plus five
on the CPU at runtime it would just set
value to seven because that would be a
lot simpler and it's definitely
something that can be calculated your in
compile time the point being that it
does not have to first do this in some
kind of order where we have value plus
plus and then that's one and therefore
since has been changed to one it now
uses that one to increment here which
means that one gets passed into here and
then increment it to two it doesn't need
to do that it's actually able to kind of
just be like okay well value zero value
plus ply okay so zero pass and zero here
busting zero here then do a little plus
plus at the end it doesn't really matter
it's allowed to do that
up until C++ 17 so the interesting thing
is if we change this to actually use the
C++ 17 standard instead of like 14 or
lower then if I run this we're actually
going to get a different result and in
fact we're going to get 1 plus 0 equals
1 because the C++ standard added a new
rule starting with C++ 17 that postfix
expressions have to be evaluated before
each other expression and with respect
to that of any other parameter meaning
they have to be done one after the other
it still doesn't really it's still it's
still not deterministic which order it
will actually be evaluated in meaning
will this be 1 and this be 0 or is it
gonna do 0 and then one for the a and B
variable respectively this water is
still undefined however they're now not
going to be the same because it has to
do one after the other let's explore
this in different compilers so to
summarize it looks like in C++ 17 which
is probably what you're using anyway at
least C++ 17 maybe you're even one of
the cool kids using the C++ 20 draft one
plus zero equals one is what we get
using visual Studios compiler now I like
using a little website here called one
box.org it's basically just a little
online compiler which has a whole bunch
of difference here both lost
as well as different compilers as you
can see if I paste our code into there
and run it using GCC and the C++ 20
draft and first of all you'll notice
this is a little bit more helpful than
the MSB C compiler which gave us no
warnings this at least tells us that
this operational value may be undefined
which you know is correct but you can
see we also get one plus zero equals one
now going back to your like CL plus 14
let's see what that gets us still 1 plus
0 equals 1 interesting and then finally
let's switch over to clang and take a
look at what clang gives us and I'll run
this in civil floss 20 here 0 plus 1
equals 1 interesting so it looks like
clang does it the other way around and
then finally if I drop back to sea
levels 14 just just to see I also get 0
plus 1 equals 1 but you can see the
clang also does in fact warn us so it's
just m/s VC who seems to just I'm not
even sure why they don't at least print
a warning for something like this but
you can see if I rebuild this in either
debug mode or release mode
it's not gonna warn me at all about
anything wrong with my code so thanks
I'm Susie so to summarize if you get
this question in a job interview or
programming test or whatever the correct
answer is it's undefined because C++
does not actually provide the superevil
specification does not actually provide
a definition for what should happen in
the situation of what order parameters
or arguments should get evaluated in but
bonus points if you mentioned that
Sables law 17 does say that these things
cannot be done at the same time that is
to say that they have to be done one
after the other but again the order is
not actually defined in the
specification which means that you
technically have no way of knowing what
this is leave your thoughts in the
comment section below in case I missed
something or I didn't test it in some
kind of mode that you that you have
tested it in then drop a comment below
let's share some knowledge in this
community because we're all in this
together
I hope you guys enjoyed this new kind of
mini suppose loss series style video let
me know other topics that you want me to
cover in the future and finally don't
forget the Skillshare is offering the
first 1,000 people who click the link in
the description below to three months of
Skillshare premium I will see you guys
next time goodbye
[Music]